Guide to the John J. Vrooman Photograph Collection 1937-1942 PR 252
New-York Historical Society
John J. Vrooman Photograph Collection
1937-1942
New-York Historical Society
PR 252
2.68 Linear feet (2 boxes)
Photographs of historic sites and houses in upstate New York.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
John J. Vrooman was an author and historian, born in 1882 in Schenectady, New York, a town founded by his ancestors. He graduated from the University of Arizona, attended Union College and received an honorary PhD from Hartwick College in Oneonta, New York. Although Vrooman traveled throughout the country, working at a variety of jobs, such as managing a ranch in Iowa, taking part in an investment business in Missouri and operating a real estate business in Mississippi, he eventually returned to Schenectady. In 1944, he accepted the position of Supervisor of Historic Sites for the New York State Education Department, a job he held until 1951.
John Vrooman's continued interest in New York State is evident in his photographs and writing. He wrote several works of fiction and non-fiction; his books all deal with historic locations and events in upstate New York. His photographs of historic sites illustrate many of his books, and were also used to illustrate material produced for the New York State Education Department. After his retirement from the Education Department, John Vrooman lectured about historic New York State, including a talk given at the New-York Historical Society in 1956 and remained active in historic studies until his death in 1960, at age 78.
Scope and Content Note
The John J. Vrooman Photograph Collection contains photographs of historically significant sites in New York State. These images show pre-Revolutionary War era landmarks throughout the Mohawk Valley and surrounding countryside. The images were used to illustrate Vrooman's book Forts and Firesides of the Mohawk Country, New York, first published in 1943.
The collection contains 56 silver gelatin prints taken by John J. Vrooman. They are all matted; most with notes regarding the image, which appear to have been written by someone other than Vrooman. During processing, the images and notes were compared to the images in Forts and Firesides of Mohawk Country, New York, and several differences were found. In those cases, the book was deemed to carry the correct information, and that information is recorded here, with the handwritten notes recorded in brackets.
The photographs have been organized alphabetically by town/site shown. The date each photograph was taken is given when available. Over time, some of the location names have changed. Current location names, as well as alternative names for sites, are listed in parentheses.
Arrangement
The photographs have been organized alphabetically by town/site shown.
Related Material
The New-York Historical Society's Library has several books written by John J. Vrooman. The Library of Congress' Prints and Photographs Division holds a small collection of Vrooman's work. Those images, taken for the Federal Writers' Project, show buildings in Crescent, New York.
Gelatin silver prints.; Mohawk River Valley (N.Y.) -- Historic buildings.; Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- Mohawk River Valley.; Historic sites -- New York (State).; Photographic prints.
- unspecified
  Scope and Contents note
  Photographs are arranged alphabetically by city.
  - ALBANY
    - Schuyler Mansion (exteriors and interiors), 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AMSTERDAM
    - Guy Park (exteriors and interiors), 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fort Johnson (exteriors and interiors), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AURIESVILLE
    - Martyr's Ravine, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CANAJOHARIE
    - Van Alstyne House, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CLINTON
    - Rev. Kirkland Cottage, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - COHOES, including Mohawk River
    - Cohoes Falls, undted (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Van Schaick House, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - COXSACKIE
    - Bronck House, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - FONDA
    - Walter Butler Home (Butlersbury), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jelles Fonda House, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - FORT PLAIN
    - Indian Castle Church, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - HOFFMAN'S FERRY (Glenville)
    - Swart House (exteriors and interiors), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - HERKIMER
    - Fort Herkimer Church (exteriors and interiors), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - JOHNSTOWN
    - Johnson Hall (exteriors and interiors), 1937, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Tryon County Courthouse (Fulton County), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Tryon County Jail, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - LITTLE FALLS
    - Herkimer Monument, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - MOHAWK
    - Shoemaker Tavern, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - NELLISTON
    - Ehle Home, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - NEWBURGH
    - Knox Headquarters, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NIAGARA-ON-THE-LAKE
    - St. Marks [The Chapel], 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - OSWEGO
    - Fort Ontario, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - PALATINE BRIDGE
    - Fort Frey [Frey Home], 1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - RENSSELAER
    - Fort Crailo (exteriors and interiors), 1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - ROME
    - Fort Bull (Wood Creek Fort), 1938 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - ROTTERDAM
    - Arent Bradt House, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Mabie House, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Van Slyck House, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - ST. JOHNSVILLE
    - Fort Kloch, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - SCHENECTEDY
    - Fuller Home, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - St. George's Church, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Governor Yates Home, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - SCOTIA
    - Abraham Glen House, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Glen Sanders House, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - STONE ARABIA
    - Reformed Dutch Church, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - TOWASENTHA
    - The Normanskill, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - TRIBES HILL
    - Dadanascara Creek, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - WATERVLIET
    - The Flatts (Schuyler Flatts Cultural Park), 1941 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - YOUNGSTOWN
    - Fort Niagara (exteriors and interiors), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 32)